<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V5.0//EN"
"../tools/docbook-dtd/dtd/docbook.dtd">
<!--
	Together Workflow Editor
	Copyright (C) 2011 Together Teamsolutions Co., Ltd.
	
	This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
	it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
	the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
	(at your option) any later version.
	
	This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the
	GNU General Public License for more details.
	
	You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
	along with this program. If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses
-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="introduction"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>What is Together Workflow Editor ?</title>

    <para>Together Workflow Editor (TWE) is a graphical editor for creating,
    editing, managing and reviewing WfMC XPDL process definition files.</para>

    <para>Workflow management is an evolving technology with lots of vendors
    claiming their approach is the best. We have chosen an approach which
    relies on WfMC and XPDL, thus supporting efforts to establish the
    standard. Together Workflow Editor is based on version 2.1 of the XPDL XML
    schema published by WfMC.</para>

    <para>The editor makes creating and editing XPDL easy. It represents all
    XPDL elements graphically through property panels and a graph component
    using BPMN graphical notation, to give the user a better understanding and
    an overview of the process definitions. Various functions help in finding
    specific activities, participants, applications, errors in the model,
    etc.</para>

    <para>The final output of the editor is an XML file (using the
    standardized WfMC XPDL schema) which can then be interpreted and executed
    by all WfMC XPDL compliant workflow engines.</para>

    <para>Together Workflow Editor accomplishes three main goals:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Reading of WfMC XPDL files (no matter from which tool they
        initially come from) from the filesystem or from the Wf-XML
        server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Graphical representation and guided editing/modelling of process
        definitions</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Writing WfMC XPDL process definition XML files to the filesystem
        or to the Wf-XML server</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>History, Presence and Future Goals</title>

    <para>Before version 4.x, Together Workflow Editor was XPDL 1 editor that
    coverd the whole XPDL 1 Meta-Model. It was the best open-source (and we
    believe also the best of all) editor which allowed any vendor to create
    the XPDL 1 based workflow processes for their workflow engines. It was
    used by many vendors to (graphically) design their process definitions.
    Beside that, it was always the example for other implementors of such
    editors to see how to correctly interpret XPDL specification.</para>

    <para>Beside the core features that allows anyone to easily model XPDL
    processes, the flexibility and configurability of the editor, that
    includes configuration by only changing the existing component's
    properties, branding, and writting a special "configuration" modes for an
    editor, makes TWE powerful, and easily adjustable for the usage with any
    specific workflow engine.</para>

    <para>The version 4.x brings XPDL 2 and BPMN support. Although not fully
    covering XPDL 2 and BPMN, TWE now allows users to use the old powers of
    the editor and new BPMN notation which goal is to standardize graphical
    process representations, and thus making them uniform accross different
    editor tools, and understandable by the users knowing BPMN
    standard.</para>

    <para>The great feature of this new version is that it automatically
    converts XPDL 1 process definitions into XPDL 2 definitions, which
    minimizes the efforts of the migration to XPDL 2. Editor currently
    supports the sub-set of XPDL 2 specification necessary to conform to
    "simple" BPMN requirements.</para>

    <para>In the future, editor will support more and more of BPMN and XPDL 2
    specification, but we will always make our focus to first implement things
    that provide the modeler writting the workflow definitions for the real
    life human workflow scenarios.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Useful links</title>

    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.wfmc.org"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The WfMC Workflow Management
    Coalition</link> promotes the advancement of process management technology
    standards and their use by the industry.</para>

    <para>The Java 2 SDK or Java 2 JRE can be downloaded from <link
    xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java</link>
    .</para>

    <para>The Together Workflow Editor home page is located at <link
    xlink:href="http://www.together.at/prod/workflow/twe"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.together.at/prod/workflow/twe</link>.</para>

    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.jgraph.com"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">JGraph</link> is an open-source
    swing graph component used in Together Workflow Editor.</para>

    <para><link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/sharkwf"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Enhydra Shark</link> - the most
    flexible Open Source WfMC XPDL workflow engine available</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
