<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V5.0//EN"
"../tools/docbook-dtd/dtd/docbook.dtd">
<!--
	Together Workflow Editor
	Copyright (C) 2011 Together Teamsolutions Co., Ltd.
	
	This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
	it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
	the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
	(at your option) any later version.
	
	This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the
	GNU General Public License for more details.
	
	You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
	along with this program. If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses
-->
<preface version="5.0" xml:id="preface" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://www.together.at/prod/workflow/twe"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Together Workflow Editor</link>
  is a visual tool for creating, managing and reviewing process definitions
  stored in WfMC XPDL syntax, using BPMN graphical notation.</para>

  <para>Put simple, Together Workflow Editor allows you to quickly create or
  view XPDL workflow definition files, check and store them for the further
  use. Once a definition is proven valid, it can be referenced by new
  definitions, thus shortening the time and effort needed to define workflow
  processes or imported into workflow engines capable of XPDL for
  execution.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>About Workflow</title>

    <para>From the <link xlink:href="http://www.wfmc.org"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Workflow Management Coalition
    website</link>:</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Why Should a Business Use Workflow ?</title>

      <para>The Evolution of Workflow Workflow Management consists of the
      automation of business procedures or "workflows" during which documents,
      information or tasks are passed from one participant to another in a way
      that is governed by rules or procedures. Workflow software products,
      like other software technologies, have evolved from diverse origins.
      While some offerings have been developed as pure workflow software, many
      have evolved from image management systems, document management systems,
      relational or object database systems, and electronic mail
      systems.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Key Benefits</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Improved efficiency - automation of many business processes
          results in the elimination of many unnecessary steps</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Better process control - improved management of business
          processes achieved through standardizing working methods and the
          availability of audit trails</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Improved customer service - consistency in the processes leads
          to greater predictability in levels of response to customers</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Flexibility - software control over processes enables their
          re-design in line with changing business needs</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Business process improvement - focus on business processes
          leads to their streamlining and simplification</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Open source</title>

    <para>Together Workflow Editor is available as an Open Source as the
    Enhydra JaWE (Java Workflow Editor) project under the GPL V3
    license.</para>

    <para><link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jawe"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Enhydra JaWE</link> is an <link
    xlink:href="http://www.opensource.org"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">open source</link> project
    hosted by <link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">SourceForge</link> , with the
    goal to deliver a production quality tool for graphical creation and
    viewing of WfMC XPDL process definitions. It results from real world
    projects in which the painful task of writing XML with general purpose XML
    editors had to be done again and again. This project is developed mainly
    by employees of <link xlink:href="http://www.together.at"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Together Teamsolutions Co.,
    Ltd</link> but also contains lots of input and improvements from the many
    users worldwide. Enhydra JaWE has a rapidly growing community and is also
    integrated in other open source projects like <link
    xlink:href="http://www.together.at/prod/server/tas"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Enhydra Server</link> - a
    professional Java and J2EE application server and <link
    xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/sharkwf"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Enhydra Shark</link> - the most
    flexible Open Source WfMC XPDL workflow engine available. Its use is <link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/philosophy.html"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">"Free as in Freedom"</link> and
    licensed under the <link xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GNU </link><link
    xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GPL V3 license</link> defined
    by the <link xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/fsf/fsf.html"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Free Software Foundation
    FSF</link>.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Commercial Support</title>

    <para>Commercial support for Together Workflow Editor including
    development of project specific extensions or integration into other
    environments and projects is offered by Together Teamsolutions Co., Ltd
    located in Pattaya/Thailand/Asia (<link
    xlink:href="mailto: office@together.at"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">mailto:
    office@together.at</link>).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Why read this book ?</title>

    <para>This book is designed to be the clear, concise explanation and
    reference to Together Workflow Editor and its usage to graphically design
    and view WfMC XPDL process definitions.</para>

    <para>We hope to answer all the questions that you might have about all
    the various XPDL elements, their meanings and how to view and edit them
    with Together Workflow Editor. In particular, this covers the following
    subjects:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The structure of the editor and its components.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Editing dialogs and property panels for all XPDL
          elements.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The relationship between XPDL and Together Workflow Editor
          including in depth explanantions of all XPDL elements.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Information how to configure and customize Together Workflow
          Editor to your needs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A step by step introduction how to build XPDL definitions from
          scratch.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>This book's audience</title>

    <para>We expect that most readers will have some familiarity with XML and
    workflow. Even if you just know what processes and activities are, you’re
    in good shape. Although this book provides basic introductions to key
    concepts, it may not suffice as your only tutorial about XPDL, XML, and
    workflow systems.</para>

    <para>Readers of this book are typically developers, workflow modelers and
    workflow system administrators.</para>

    <para>Some sections in this book describe certain environments like
    Microsoft Windows or Linux, although there is nothing about Together
    Workflow Editor that makes it unsuitable for the Mac or any other
    environment of your choice, as long as the defined software prerequisites
    (basically a JRE - Java Runtime Environment 1.8) are met.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Organization of this book</title>

    <para>This book is divided into the following chapters:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Introduction - What is Together Workflow Editor all about
        ?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Installation Guide - How to install TWE</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>User Interface - Explanation of the user interface components,
        menus and toolbars</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Dialogs and Property Panels - How to handle editor dialogs and
        XPDL property panels</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>XPDL Elements - What they are, how they are related and how to
        create, edit and view them</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>XPDL from Scratch - How to create your first XPDL file</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configuration - How to tailor the Editor to your needs</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Customization - How to extend the Editor with additional
        functionality</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Extended Attribute Reference - XPDL Extended Attributes used by
        the Editor itself</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Build Guide - How to compile, build and package your own version
        of TWE from the source code</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Release notes - Notes about the major changes in each
        release</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>

  <!--
    <sect1>
      <title>Conventions used in this book</title>

      <para>to be done</para>
    </sect1>
-->

  <sect1>
    <title>Request for Comments</title>

    <para>Please help us to improve future editions of this book by reporting
    any errors, inaccuracies, bugs, misleading or confusing statements, and
    plain old typos that you find. Email your findings to <link
    xlink:href="mailto:twe@together.at"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">twe@togetherteam.co.th</link>.
    Thanks.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Acknowledgements</title>

    <para>Many thanks go to the Swiss company <link
    xlink:href="http://www.abacus.ch"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ABACUS</link> for sponsoring
    major parts of the Together Workflow Editor Version 2.0
    development.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>About the Authors</title>

    <para>All authors are directly involved in one way or the other into the
    core development of Together Workflow Editor and Enhydra JaWE.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Together Teamsolutions Co., Ltd</title>

    <para>Together Teamsolutions Co., Ltd has been active for many years
    primarily in the area of workflow, database and document management
    solutions.</para>

    <para>In addition to the organizational and implementation services, these
    application areas are supplemented by the operation of solutions (system
    rollout, 24x7 hotline, training) as well as product development,
    consulting services (business process analysis and modelling),
    publications and presentations. The associated topics needed for real
    world projects, e.g. imaging, OCR, host integration, archiving, computer
    telephone integration, digital signatures, backup, performance tuning,
    reporting, systems administration and hardware sizing are also covered,
    continuously maintained and expanded.</para>

    <para>Together Teamsolutions Co., Ltd is directly involved into the
    development of the XPDL standards specification.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Enhydra</title>

    <para>The Enhydra.org project has its focus on E-Business middleware
    software. It now consists of many developers from over 50 countries. Many
    of these are able to offer commercial products, support, consulting and
    training.</para>

    <para>Enhydra.org started with Enhydra, the first and leading Open Source
    Java/XML application server. It was initially created by Lutris
    Technologies, Inc. which already disappeared from the market. After 4
    years in development it was open sourced on Janurary 15th 1999. They named
    the technology "Enhydra" after the California sea otter (Enhydra Lutris) -
    a popular inhabitant of Santa Cruz.</para>

    <para>Big parts of Enhydra development are now sponsored by Together
    Teamsolutions Co., Ltd located in Thailand. One of the outcomes of this
    sponsorship is Enhydra JaWE / Together Workflow Editor.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>JaWE</title>

    <para>JaWE - Java Workflow Editor - is the Open Source project of Together
    Workflow Editor. It is fully useable to edit, view and save complete XPDL
    files and licensed under GPL V3. Sources are publicly available in the
    projects CVS repository hosted at SourceForge</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>WfMC - The Workflow Management Coalition</title>

    <para>Founded in August 1993, the Workflow Management Coalition (WfMC) is
    a non-profit, global organization of adopters, developers, consultants,
    analysts and university/research groups engaged in Business Process
    Management (BPM). Workflow or BPM is the technology that supports people
    to do their work. Resulting benefit is more efficiency, traceability,and
    quality improvements.</para>

    <para>WfMC creates and contributes to process related standards and
    educates on the benefits of process automation. WfMC is the only standards
    organization that concentrates purely on process. WfMC created XPDL and
    Wf-XML and had influence on BPMN, OMG workflow interface, ASAP and many
    other process related standards.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>JGraph</title>

    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.jgraph.com"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">JGraph</link> is a powerful,
    easy-to-use, feature-rich and standards-compliant open source graph
    component available for Java. This library is used in Together Workflow
    Editor for graphical representation of process layouts (graph
    component).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Docbook</title>

    <para>This book was written using <link
    xlink:href="http://www.docbook.org"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">DocBook</link> and the <link
    xlink:href="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">XML Mind XML
    Editor</link>.</para>
  </sect1>
</preface>
