<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V5.0//EN"
"../tools/docbook-dtd/dtd/docbook.dtd">
<!--
	Together Workflow Editor
	Copyright (C) 2011 Together Teamsolutions Co., Ltd.
	
	This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
	it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
	the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
	(at your option) any later version.
	
	This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
	but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
	MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the
	GNU General Public License for more details.
	
	You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
	along with this program. If not, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses
-->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="customization"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Customization</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Need for customization</title>

    <para>In order to make the life easier for the XPDL developers, and to
    make developing of XPDLs less error prone, it could be a good idea to
    customize TWE. One way of customization can be introduction of new
    activity types (e.g. automated activities for sending e-mails with
    customized property panels for entering all the information, a special
    kind of deadline element, a special XPDL template for creating a new
    workflow process, ...).</para>

    <para>Thanks to its internal architecture, TWE can be easily customized in
    order to support these requirements.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Example - activity for sending an e-mail</title>

    <para>To illustrate previous statement, let's say that in all of our
    processes, we are intensivelly using Tool activity for sending
    e-mails.</para>

    <para>If we use standard TWE implementation, everytime we want to insert
    such activity in the process (e.g. via Graph component), we first need to
    insert a standard Tool activitiy using TWE's Graph component toolbox.
    After that, we need to open the property panel for the activity, go to the
    Type section, and create a new Tool for this activity. When new Tool is
    created, we need to edit it, where we need to select a reference to the
    Application definition for sending e-mails, and than to create as many
    ActualParameters for the Tool as there are FormalParameters for the Send
    E-Mail Application definition. And finally, we need to enter appropriate
    values for this ActualParameters (either a references to the variables, or
    some text expressions).</para>

    <para>You have to admit that there is a lot of work to do, and it can be
    quite anoying if you have to do it many times. Also, it is error
    prone.</para>

    <para>What we can do is to extend standard TWE functionallity, and to
    introduce a new type of an activity for sending e-mails, which will be the
    customization of the standard Tool activity. We can offer a new button in
    Graph's toolbar for creating such kind of an activity. This button would
    have a special icon, and e-mail-ing activity when inserted into graph
    would also have this icon to be diferentiated amongst others. Also, when
    such activity is created, its XPDL content would be automatically
    pre-filled, so it would always have a Tool which would reference the
    Application for sending an e-mails, and this Tool would already have a
    default values for all necessary ActualParameters. But this is not all, we
    can also offer a special property panel for entering e-mail parameters
    (ActualParameters) - e.g, we can have a combo-box with a list of e-mail
    addresses (which could be filled through the LDAP), we can have a text box
    for entering mail subject, and a text area for entering mail
    content.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Available customizations</title>

    <para>TWE distribution comes with several customized configurations. You
    can switch from one configuration to another one if you select
    Settings-&gt;Configuration and select desired configuration. TWE will be
    re-configured to use selected configuration.</para>

    <para>Available configurations are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>default - default TWE configuration.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>shark - configuration specific to TWE usage with Shark engine.
        Includes special property panels for editing some of extended
        attributes, shark specific restrictions and validation according to
        these restrictions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>samples-loopactivity - sample configuration that introduces new
        type of activity along with the special icon for this activity and
        special property panel for editing its properties.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
