<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>TWE release notes</title>

  <chapter>
    <title>System requirements</title>

    <para>The minimum recommended system configuration is:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>128 MB RAM</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>200 MHz processor or better</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>70 MB disk space (see note below)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Java Runtime Environment (JRE) 1.4.x</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>

    <para>Note that the disk space specified above reflects the minimum system
    requirements to install and run the TWE. A minimum installation consists
    of:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>JRE 1.4.x (approximately 45 MB)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TWE (approximately 25 MB)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 3.2-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- code restructured</para>

    <para>- updated base component's JAR files to more recent versions (batik,
    ant, itext, xerces, saxon, fop, java help, jedit syntax and JGraph). Code
    modified accordingly.</para>

    <para>- updated build scripts (build procedure changes)</para>

    <para>- new splash screen</para>

    <para>- project moved to source forge</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 3.1-3</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- updated build scripts</para>

    <para>- sharkxpdlmodel.jar version 3.1-3 included</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 3.1-2</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- updated build scripts</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 3.1-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- updated build scripts</para>

    <para>- minor changes</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 3.0-2</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- introduced possibility to start JaWE in non-frame/dialog
    mode</para>

    <para>- NSIS tool is updated to version 2.46</para>

    <para>- readregistry.nsi script is improved - readregistry.exe is able to
    get information about Java from 64bit part of the registry.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 3.0-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- Moved completely to open-source, with license changed to GPL
    V3</para>

    <para>- All the sources available on OW2 including the ones for branding
    TWE</para>

    <para>- Included missing features of JPEd (editor based on previous
    community version of TWE):</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>No annoying 30 seconds splash screen</para>

        <para>since now community version of TWE has all the fatures
        professional version had, and does not display annoying splash
        screen</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Do not lose layout during load/save operations:</para>

        <para>this version of TWE by default doesn't lose layouting
        information, there is a special "configuration" called "Pure XPDL"
        where all TWE specific extended attributes are not persisted into
        XPDL, including the ones that cause lost of layouting information
        during load/save)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Plugins interface allows you to write wizards, custom XPDL
        elements editors, custom tooltips, custom views. With it you can
        easily make jped company requirements</para>

        <para>TWE architecture is pluggable, thus one can write any kind of
        plug-ins, can provide custom XPDL element editors (additional ones
        comparing to JPEd and previous TWE community version exist in this new
        version), can configure different tooltip generator etc...</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Generate PDF reports of your workflow. Get a complete view of
        your workflow in a ready to print format. Plugins can be used also to
        customize PDF outputs.</para>

        <para>The part of the code is taken from JPEd and included in
        TWE</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A fully customizable interface, using properties file and system
        properties: - Restrict the availabe actions in interface or to extend
        them at glance, depending your target users. - Easily create a custom
        layout that is easier to manipulate for end-users. - Combined with a
        wizard plugin, you can prefill an XPDL or auto update it, letting user
        concentrate only on you core buisness.</para>

        <para>TWE has ability to configure user interface through property
        files, to restrict/extend available actions or to define which parts
        of XPDL to hide to the user, define layouts, and also by custom core
        plug-ins.</para>

        <para>It has a powerful templating mechanism, where one can easily add
        a new type of prefilled XPDL object, and in the case of activities to
        easily include it in the toolbox just by configuration and property
        files</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Generate real vectorial (SVG) output of graph, including the Ids
        of activity, participants and transitions. (Zoom at any level with any
        SVG enabled tool or use it in a workflow engine web interface to
        highlight current status with just a simple svg stylesheet.)</para>

        <para>This part of code was taken from JPEd and included in TWE</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Quick search dropdowns make it easy to handle long list of
        participants</para>

        <para>Already existed in TWE community</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For shark users, an integrated form editor which also add
        additional informations in tooltips and PDF</para>

        <para>TWE has a special shark configuration, where not only this
        feature is provided, but also customized panels adjusted to Shark's
        extended attributes and other options, special Shark XPDL validation,
        etc.</para>

        <para>The same thing is done for WfMOpen (special WfMOpen
        configuration)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>See the XPDL fragment of each element you are editing, know
        exactly what you are doing at XPDL level in each dialog.</para>

        <para>In TWE, XPDL View shows the fragment of any selected element in
        XPDL</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Condition editor, gives you a dropdown box to select workflow
        variables and provides syntax highlighting for scripted
        conditions</para>

        <para>This feature existed in TWE professional version and thus
        appears in this version now.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Customize JPEd logo to fit your company need, provide a splash
        logo when editor is loading, using a simple System property</para>

        <para>TWE sources now have a "branding" capability. You can brand the
        whole project (icons, setup, splash logo, about box information) and
        get setup.exe file for installing such product</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>- XPDL Model code moved to Shark (LGPL licensed) and now taken from
    Shark</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.5-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- Highlighting java/javascript syntax in fields for entering
    expression criteria (Transition conditions, deadline expressions, actual
    parameters)</para>

    <para>- Activity's performer field now comes with higlight editor for
    java/javascript, and buttons to chose participant and variables</para>

    <para>- Problems component view now depends on selection (Package/Workflow
    Process/ActivitySet)</para>

    <para>- Improved expression's validation</para>

    <para>- Implemented table sorting</para>

    <para>- Improved D&amp;D of table entries</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.4-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with
    TWE.</para>

    <para>- Shark configuration adjustement to new shark 2.2-1version:
    PROCESS_ID and ACTIVITY_ID can be used in transition condition's and as
    actual parameters</para>

    <para>- Implemented possibility to switch DataField to a FormalParameter
    and vice-versa</para>

    <para>- Core extended to support new ext. attribute types per their parent
    object (Activity, Application, ...)</para>

    <para>- Improved property panels</para>

    <para>- Serbian property file renamed to have extension "sr" instead of
    "sh"</para>

    <para>- Fixed bug with external packages (when newly opened XPDL has the
    external package with the same Id but different location as the one opened
    before)</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.3-2</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- Implementation-Version attribute included into MANIFEST of jar
    files</para>

    <para>- Improved installation procedure - language dependent stuff and
    links to the application from start menu</para>

    <para>- Fixed bug in SharkXPDLObjectFactory - wasn't able to properly use
    Activity's "Variables" tab</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bug in ExternalPkgRelations component (NPE when selecting
    Arbitrary Expression Participipant)</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.3-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- Added new component for LDAP participant handling (the old action
    from the menu bar removed)</para>

    <para>- Option buttons displayed for the language and configuration
    choices (the selected language/configuration is marked)</para>

    <para>- Language switch is now possible in run-time</para>

    <para>- Added configuration file which contains information about
    configuration name to be displayed for the configuration choices and in
    the title bar.</para>

    <para>- Architectural changes to support add-on architecture</para>

    <para>- Community version now can also display the result of References
    and Search action</para>

    <para>- Core code is improved so now it is possible to add new object
    types without coding (just by configuration). Now we use XML templates for
    new object types (XPDL fragments).</para>

    <para>- Top tree elements now have '-' displayed if they contain
    sub-elements</para>

    <para>- Portuguese translation included</para>

    <para>- Solved language usage issues with parser, JOptionPane,
    JFileChooser, missing strings,etc.</para>

    <para>- Added additional language property file where you can define
    additional language specific properties per the configuration.</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bug when adding external package which contains processes
    with activity sets and when "automatic layouting" is turned on.</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bug in handling of transient packages that appeared when
    you have transient package in the pool and you try to open XPDL from
    unexisting file - this caused all packages to unload from XMLInterface and
    after it happens it was possible to have two XPDLs with same Id in
    TWE.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.2-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- Implemented Search capability for searching XPDL elements based on
    specified criteria.</para>

    <para>- In TWE's default configuration/mode, workflow_patterns.xpdl is
    present in Transient package pool</para>

    <para>- Improvement: when configured to save XPDLs with namespace prefix
    and if XPDL didn't have xpdl namespace defined TWE now automatically adds
    this namespace.</para>

    <para>- More icons for XPDL entities are shown in DetailedPackageNavigator
    view</para>

    <para>- New configuration parameter for validating if variable (DataField
    or WorkflowProcess's FormalParameter) is not used anywhere in XPDL (nor as
    actual parameter or inside expression). If it is not used, warning is
    reported when validating XPDL.</para>

    <para>- Icons defined for all entries in menu bar</para>

    <para>- Some shortcut/accelerator keys have changed</para>

    <para>- Expand all/Collapse all are now context sensitive in relation to
    selected tree-node</para>

    <para>- Top tree elements now have '-' displayed if they contain
    sub-elements</para>

    <para>- Switched to 2.9 version of xerces</para>

    <para>- Spanish translation included</para>

    <para>- XMLInterface changed - removed method getIdFromFile (it is now a
    static method of XMLUtil class)</para>

    <para>- Code corrections based on FindBugs report</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bug with reading of language property files from jar file -
    if there are spaces in the path where TWE is installed they were not
    read</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bug in XMLCheckBoxPanel - whenever mouse was over, an apply
    button was enabled as if something has changed in a panel</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bug that was introduced in previous version and appeares
    when there are external packages defined and Id of the main package is
    changed</para>

    <para>- Fixed: when trying to save read-only document TWE didn't complain
    but the changes were not saved to a document</para>

    <para>- fixed bug in Shark configuration - bug fix in Shark configuration
    (related with deletion of ext. attribs)</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.1-1-bugfix build 20061110</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- fixed bug in Transient Package Pool componenet that was
    manifesting during usage of Common expression and Free Text expression
    participants</para>

    <para>- fixed bug in Shark configuration - when you delete variable from
    'Variable' tab, it was not removed from the table</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.1-1</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- added Transient Packag Pool component for
    displaying/adding/removing transient packages, and introduced
    configuration option to define transient packages that will be loaded by
    default on TWE startup</para>

    <para>- added additional graph actions to select activities for selected
    transitions and vice versa</para>

    <para>- improved shark configuration (added new features to better support
    shark professional version and new shark web admin application)</para>

    <para>- improved documentation</para>

    <para>- demo version gets demo documentation</para>

    <para>- when creating new Package, xpdl namespace is added by
    default</para>

    <para>- improved windows setup.exe distribution - user is asked if he
    wants to add desktop and qucik launch shortcut</para>

    <para>- code re-organization</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bug in XMLInterfaceForJDK13-&gt;getPackageById()
    method</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.0-6</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- property file location moved from %USER_HOME%/.JaWE to
    %TWE_HOME%/conf/xxx.</para>

    <para>- enabled re-configuration at runtime - possible configurations are
    placed in sub-folders of %TWE_HOME%/conf, default configuration is written
    in %TWE_HOME%/conf/defaultconf</para>

    <para>- beside default configuration, added shark configuration, wfmopen
    configuration, samples-loopactivity and purexpdl configuration</para>

    <para>- shark configuration is adjustment of jawe to shark-engine
    restrictions + swing admin ext. attribs. Automatic change of ext. attribs
    when variable Id changes; validation on this special ext. attribs and
    validation according to shark restrictions</para>

    <para>- wfmopen configuration is adjustment of jawe to wfmopen-engine
    restrictions + special ext. attribs. validation on this special ext.
    attribs and validation according to wfmopen restrictions</para>

    <para>- improved simple graph layout action's algorithm (never goes back
    in the swimline whenever possible, when there is a split inside same
    swimline - new rows are created, handling of start/end bubbles
    improved)</para>

    <para>- included David Delbecq's improved drop-down list (switching from
    menu-items to search-able list when there are 30 or more items) for
    inserting participants and selecting activity sets in graph
    component</para>

    <para>- included David Delbecq's improved drop-down list (switching from
    menu-items to search-able list when there are 30 or more items) for
    selecting packages and workflow processes in info-bar</para>

    <para>- Search panel renamed to References</para>

    <para>- Documentation links in windows setup now reference full HTML
    document</para>

    <para>- API entry in Windows dist is renamed to Together Workflow Editor
    Profesional API</para>

    <para>- TWE stores new ext. attrib. information in XPDL for determining
    configuration used to create this XPDL</para>

    <para>- added possibility to chose icon for the activity from the list of
    available icons</para>

    <para>- added workflow_patterns.xpdl file (originally created for shark
    distribution)</para>

    <para>- defined keyboard shortcuts for almost all menu items</para>

    <para>- improved automatic insertion of start/end markers</para>

    <para>- code re-organization (introduction of new classes and
    configuration properties)</para>

    <para>- Fixed: rare bug in Graph component when start/end bubbles are the
    only one placed within FreeTextExpression participant</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.0-5</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- introduced possibility to chose when adding external packages if
    external package will be "transient" (it won't be saved into the file, but
    its purpose will be to provide a container where from you can copy common
    elements)</para>

    <para>- introduction of compound icons (no need to define special icon for
    errors and warnings)</para>

    <para>- Minor code changes/reorganization.</para>

    <para>- improved automatical insertion of Start/End markers</para>

    <para>- improved property panel for defining workflow relevant data:
    sub-panel for entering initial value is now bigger</para>

    <para>- improved usage of LDAP connection: better support of
    ActiveDirectory search, added LDAPReferralHandling property, password
    field hidden</para>

    <para>- Fixed: bugs in usage of LDAP connection for inserting participants
    (user+password authentication didn't work, search scope didn't
    work)</para>

    <para>- Fixed: Graph component's tooltip bug in Zoom In/Out mode.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.0-4</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- New possibility to save XPDLs with xpdl namespace prefix (TWE by
    default configured to do so)</para>

    <para>- Added language property files for French and German
    language.</para>

    <para>- Minor code changes/reorganization.</para>

    <para>- Now using Xerces 2.8</para>

    <para>- Fixed: problem with overlapping dialogs after loading XPDL
    file.</para>

    <para>- Fixed: Enter key didn't work in a table panels</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.0-3</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- Added language property file for Serbian language.</para>

    <para>- Code changes/reorganization.</para>

    <para>- Fixed: if there were many participants in XPDL, pop-up menu for
    showing participants that can be inserted into graph couldn't show all of
    them.</para>

    <para>- Fixed: TWE didn't change the references when the Id of
    TypeDeclaration is changed.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new in TWE 2.0-2</title>

    <para>This chapter lists the new or updated features associated with TWE
    .</para>

    <para>- added WfXML authentication.</para>

    <para>- default condition type for newly inserted transitions (via graph)
    is not set which means that by default unconditional transition is being
    inserted (previously default type was 'Condition')</para>

    <para>- added new validation option called 'ValidateConditionByType'
    (which default value is true); when set to true, TWE will generate warning
    in following cases:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>transition's condition type is not set (unconditional
        transition) and there is condition expression defined</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>transition's condition type is set to 'Condition' (conditional
        transition) and there is no condition expression defined</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>transition's condition type is set to 'Exception' (exceptional
        transition) and there is no condition expression defined</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>transition's condition type is set to 'Otherwise' and there is
        condition expression defined</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>transition's condition type is set to 'Default exception' and
        there is condition expression defined</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>- allowed deletion of invalid ExternalPackage elements (when there
    is no external package referenced)</para>

    <para>- improved conversion of XPDL files from old JaWE versions -&gt;
    Start/End markers are now properly positioned</para>

    <para>- generally improved XPDL validation</para>

    <para>- improved procedure of closing changed XPDLs - now TWE doesn't ask
    you to enter the file name if this is an XPDL opened from an existing
    file</para>

    <para>- logging manager implementiation is now using Java logging instead
    system.out</para>

    <para>- fixed NPE in LDAP connection</para>

    <para>- fixed rare bug with repositioning of Objects in the table or
    list</para>

    <para>- fixed bug with the displaying names of a certain extended
    attributes (i.e. if you defined ext. attrib. with name 'm', afterwards
    you'll see 'minute' instead of 'm' displayed in ext. attrib. property
    panel)</para>

    <para>- fixed bug with Graph validation of Start/End markers during the
    save of Packages marked as 'Released' (TWE allowed saving of incorrect
    package)</para>

    <para>- fixed bug with XPDL validation of Tool's Actual-&gt;Formal
    parameter mapping during the save of Packages marked as 'Released' (TWE
    allowed saving of incorrect package)</para>

    <para>- fixed problem with de-selection of graph during undo</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation, platform, and system information</title>

    <section>
      <title>Installation</title>

      <para>On Windows, TWE can be installed either using EXE distribution
      setup, or un-zipping ZIP distribution and executing configure script
      afterwards. On Linux, you can do the same with RPM and TAR.GZ
      distributions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>OS support</title>

      <para>TWE is tested on Windows 2000/XP/Vista, as well as on various
      Linux distributions.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JDKs</title>

      <para>Tested with Sun JDK 1.4.x and higher on Windows 2000/XP/Vista,
      Linux</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
